sign.
Oh, my bad. What I was saying is it
feels wrong to be stuck inside all the
time around artificial lights. But could
it not just feel wrong, but be wrong for
our body? Well, a brand spanking new
trial has finally tested if being
indoors around artificial light all day
is having direct impact on your
metabolism and thereby your health. I'd
like to walk you through the most
telling findings, but then I'd like to
also show you a very easy experiment
that you can run on yourself to see if
this would work on you, as well as some,
well, maybe surprising revelations. The
researchers did a fun experiment where
they had a group of people come into an
office building as you can see here. And
they were told to work at a desk in a
natural in a naturally lit room with big
windows as seen here or in a pure
artificial light like this. And then
they worked in these conditions for 5
days. Now their nutrition was perfectly
controlled throughout those 5 days as
well. Then before and after the
experiment they had a number of health
measures taken. For example, blood
glucose levels. Now I think the most
striking visual is the difference in the
light exposure is this one. The green
and yellow is where the greatest light
intensity was and the vertical axis is
the wavelengths of light. The left is
the natural light from the sun coming
through the window and the right is the
artificial light. So no sun exposure.
It's striking. The artificial light
supplies only a few wavelengths of
light. The general idea here is that
sunlight is the ultimate sight gaba
which translates literally from German
to timegiver which sounds like a grand
force from a Marvel movie or something.
Dad sight ga.
It works to combat Doctor Strange by
giving or taking away time for Doctor
Strange to manipulate. And it
manipulates him by only giving him dark
times to work with. Yeah, there's
something there. I know it, but well, we
have to carry on. In physiology, your
eyes detect light, especially blue
light. So, this wavelength and as you
can tell, there's plenty of it in
natural light, but little in artificial
light. Anyway, your eyes detect light
through specialized cells called
melanopsin retinal ganglen cells, which
send a signal to a section of your brain
called the super kaismatic nucleus. Now,
don't worry about the names. This
nucleus in your brain is responsible for
releasing hormones and furthering
signals throughout the body that change
your body's temperature, but also
control internal clocks within your
organs like your liver, your kidneys,
pancreas, muscle, and more. Now, if the
nucleus sends strong signals, the entire
body is in sync. Meaning that the
clocks, which are genes encoded in your
genome, will produce proteins that
regulate your metabolism. For example,
proteins, enzymes involved in blood
sugar regulation will be increased in
the muscle cells to take up more sugar
glucose out of the bloodstream. I'm
skipping over a lot of details here, but
that's the gist. The main point here
being that if we eliminate this
wavelength of light that is supposed to
activate cells in our eyes to then
activate an area of our brain that
controls all of our organ systems,
internal clocks, are there consequences?
It seems reasonable to think that. So
what happened? Well, let's stick with
the blood glucose. This is a continuous
measure of blood glucose or more
specifically the interstatial glucose,
which is the glucose found directly
around the cells. It comes from the
blood, but it's not a direct measure of
the blood. It's one layer deeper.
Anyway, you can see that over the 5
days, the glucose levels are roughly the
same and follow similar patterns. That
alone is fascinating simply because it
shows how predictably our body operates
if all else is kept equal. In the end,
while the red line, the natural light
condition does seem to dip slightly
below the artificial light condition, it
never reaches statistical significance.
That said, the researchers did compare
the amount of time that glucose levels
remained in the normal healthy range.
And we see that the red dots are higher,
indicating that when the participants
were exposed to natural light, their
glucose levels were better controlled.
So that's pretty interesting because it
tells us that there may be some
subclinical effects that may be
happening, things that aren't apparent
on a simple one-time blood measure, but
may be happening underneath everything
nonetheless. Personally, what I found mo
the most interesting was the impact on
metabolism. So check this out. We're
looking at calorie expenditure over the
day. Notice how both lines are right on
top of one another. That means that
there's no difference. Or is there?
Okay, fair enough. The calories used or
expended are the same. But what about
the source of those calories? On the
left is the body's carbohydrate
metabolism and on the right is the
body's fat metabolism. Note that they
are exact opposites of one another,
meaning that the blue line exposed to
artificial light tends to change
metabolism toward carbohydrate
metabolism while sacrificing fat
metabolism. Those exposed to natural
light experience the opposite. Their
body uses more fat metabolism. Now, we
can't necessarily make judgments on one
being better than the other since they
both serve a purpose, but in a quiet,
relaxed state, it's generally seen as
more normal to have fat burning for
energy. But we do now know that light by
itself changes our metabolism, which is
a pretty remarkable finding. Beyond
that, it was also shown that several
sight gaba molecules and genes were
changed with artificial light exposure.
Now, we've gone over several changes,
some quite intriguing, and considering
the context that we're discussing, this
all is based on simply changing a light
source. It does leave an impression.
However, there are a few things to point
out here that I think are important.
Before we get into that, I have a deeper
analysis for of the study, including the
impact that it might have on sleep,
insulin resistance, related molecules,
and more. It's available if you're a
physionic insider, my premium research
platform. In fact, all my videos get the
full spa treatment there, including full
articles, one paragraph summaries, an
accompanying monthly podcast that covers
everything, and much more. As you can
see here, if you're so inclined to learn
your body like never before and how to
help it be healthier and higher
performing, then join the Physionic
Insiders. The link to join is in the
description box. Okay, back to it.
First, yes, there are changes, but I
have to admit the effects we're seeing
are pretty minor, sometimes a little
chuckle worthy. For example, uh when we
looked at the blood glucose levels, the
researchers did a lot of usual measures
for glucose and found diff no
differences between the exposure. So
then they started looking at more niche
changes like the amount of time that
glucose was below or above normal values
within the day or looking at a series of
genes and detecting only a few changes
while many others are not impacted at
all. I don't know about you, but
I'm not impressed with tiny changes that
we have to hunt through multiple
experiments to find minor effects,
especially as the study was primarily
done in people with severe insulin
resistance, diabetics. So, that critique
mentioned, I can also offer a
counterargument. The counterargument
goes something like this.
Yeah, but all I have to do is look
outside and enjoy a nice view or at the
very least be exposed to some natural
light. It's not like you have to do a 60
sprints, a barrel roll over coals, lift
a boulder over your head 10 times and
squat an elephant. You just have to turn
around and face a window. That's it. In
addition, this study only lasted 5 days
in each exposure. Could the effect grow
over time? I doubt it would ever cure
anyone of diabetes or something to that
effect, but it seems reasonable that
this small change could have a small,
very low barrier to entry difference.
So, even with the keep in mind weak
results, it seems just about a
no-brainer to still do it. Try to spend
a bit more time in natural light rather
than artificial light. But let's say
that you're a person who wants to verify
these kinds of things on yourself.
What would be a way that you could do
that? Well, the best way would be to use
a continuous glucose monitor and run an
easy experiment on yourself. You'd want
to keep your nutrition identical
throughout the experiment. And also
consider running the experiment longer
than 5 days for each condition. There
would be two conditions. One where
you're primarily exposed to artificial
light, preferably with no blue light,
but probably devoid of most wavelengths.
And then the other condition is the
obvious one, sitting next to or in front
of a window with natural light coming
in. Then you want to track two things.
One, the average blood glucose over time
and compare the two. Now, the study did
not identify any differences, but those
are total results. So, it's possible
that there were meaningful differences
for some participants. Plus, if you run
the experiment longer, you may detect a
difference. And two, where the study did
find a difference was the amount of time
spent in the normal glucose range. So
for blood glucose in this study, it was
a wide range of 72 to 140 mg per
deciliter or 4 to 7.8 mill per liter.
Why this odd range? Because the
researchers weren't looking at normal
fasting blood glucose. They were
including values that would appear after
eating as well. This is also why keeping
your nutrition and as many var variables
as possible the same is critical.
Anyway, if you run the test on yourself,
let us know in the comments. I'd be very
interested to know if anyone detects a
physiological difference. Yeah. Anyway,
so if you're looking for another easy
way of improving your metabolic health,
look no further than this video right
here. Click before the tight gaba gets
you. I hope this was informative. Thanks
for tuning in. I'll catch you in the
next one. Bye.